<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Modest proposal for the more certain and yet more easie provision for the poor and likewise for the better suppression of thieves, diminishers and corrupters of the coyn, and other lewd livers : tending much to the advancement of trade, especially in the most profitable part of it, the manufactures of the kingdom.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B26917</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18483263</idno>
  <idno type="VID">206544</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240854263</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2369</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">18483263</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B26917)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 206544)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1639:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Modest proposal for the more certain and yet more easie provision for the poor and likewise for the better suppression of thieves, diminishers and corrupters of the coyn, and other lewd livers : tending much to the advancement of trade, especially in the most profitable part of it, the manufactures of the kingdom.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 25 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Southby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695/6 [i.e. 1696]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Poor --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:206544:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:206544:1"/>
            <p>A <hi>Modest Proposal</hi> For the more Certain and yet more Easie Provision for the Poor.</p>
            <p>AND Likewise for the better Suppression of <hi>Thieves, Diminishers</hi> and <hi>Corrupters of the Coyn,</hi> and other <hi>Lewd Livers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tending much to the Advancement of TRADE, Especially in the most Profitable part of it, <hi>The Manufactures of the Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Southby,</hi> at the <hi>Harrow</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1695/6.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:206544:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:206544:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T generally happens, that Projectors are so Fond of their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, that they Overlook all the Weaknesses of them. I will not therefore presume, that my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posal is without many Exceptions; indeed, hardly any Thing is Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected at the First Heat; and, perhaps, had I allow'd my self Time, I might have brought <hi>This</hi> into a little better Form. But having seen the <hi>Votes of the House of Commons</hi> of the <hi>31st</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> which, I believe, were by the Good Providence of GOD put into the Minds of that <hi>Honourable House,</hi> as a <hi>Blessing</hi> on the <hi>Religious Fast</hi> they kept the day before; I made haste to speak a Word in season, since Timely Hints
<pb facs="tcp:206544:3"/>are better than the most Consummate Works that come too late. And if I can but give the least Hint from whence a <hi>Good Design</hi> may be formed, for the Compassing the Ends I propose, I have done a <hi>Good Service</hi> to the <hi>Publick;</hi> for which, I hope, all my Faults may be Pardoned.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proposal">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:206544:3"/>
            <head>A <hi>Modest Proposal,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IT cannot be deny'd, but that We have already many good Laws for the <hi>Relief of the Poor</hi> in their last Necessities; and likewise there are many Bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Donations, and a general good Inclination to Charity in the People of this Land (especially when they think their Charity will not be abused) whereby a more liberal and plentiful Provision for the <hi>Poor</hi> is or might be made. There are also good Laws, if well executed, for the Correction of Idle and Riotous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons: And, for those whose Idleness and Riot ha h led them into the high Crimes of <hi>Robbery, Burglary, Clipping</hi> and <hi>Coyning,</hi> and the like, our Laws have provided the Punishment of Death, which being look'd upon as the highest Punishment, hath been thought the most likely to deter Men from these Crimes, so mischievous to the <hi>Publick Good</hi> and <hi>Safety.</hi> But yet it must be confess'd, that in many places the Poor are not sufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for; That the Land is weaken'd and wasted by <hi>Sloth</hi> and <hi>Riot;</hi> and that the number of those high Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals, such as <hi>Robbers, House-breakers, Clippers</hi> and <hi>Coiners,</hi> and the like, doth daily rather encrease than di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minish. And indeed, it cannot be otherwise, while there
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:206544:4"/>an Habit of Idleness and Luxury, out of which it is next to impossible for them ever to deliver themselves, tho' you provide never so many Punishments to terrifie them. The great Defect then, as I conceive, of all the Remedies we have at present for these Evils lies in this, That there is no effectual course taken to keep persons from getting into an Habit of <hi>Idleness</hi> and <hi>Luxury;</hi> or, when they are got into it, to pluck them out of it whether they will or no. To speak more particularly, we are, as I apprehend, wanting in these Six things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That persons that cannot live without Relief have not been provided of some Work or other which they might be capable of doing, and also forced to do to help something towards their Relief.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Persons taking Relief have not yet been obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to live on such cheap Provisions as they might be well sustained with.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That persons living Idely and Extravagantly have not been sufficiently enquir'd into, and oblig'd to live within the compass of what either their Labour or Estate can well maintain.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That there hath been no Care taken to maintain on the publick Charge the Children of such persons who have more than their honest Labour and Industry can support.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That for those persons whose Idleness and Luxury hath led them into the aforesaid Crimes of <hi>Robbery, Clip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping,</hi> and <hi>Coyning,</hi> and the like, there have not been the most proper Punishments used, either to amend them, or deter others from the same Wickedness. But,</p>
            <p n="6">6. And chiefly, the great Defect has been in that the most proper Overseers, and such as would and could make it their Business continually to keep the Methods for the Relief of the <hi>Poor</hi> and Punishment of the <hi>Wicked,</hi> on
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:206544:4"/>foot, and in perpetual execution, have not been consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted.</p>
            <p>I will therefore begin with this last Point: And it is my Opinion, That not only the <hi>Justices of the Peace</hi> (who are oftentimes Men of considerable quality, and large Estates, and, consequently, call'd from their Homes by their Business, and some of them by long attendance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Parliament) should have the care of this matter; but that also there should be a great number of Magistrates of an Inferiour Rank created for this purpose, who may be termed <hi>Fathers of the Poor, Correcters and Amenders of the Wicked,</hi> or by any other Name that Authority thinks convenient. These Inferiour Magistrates I would have chosen out of Men that are worth 1000 <hi>l.</hi> or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, and they may be chosen by the Inhabitants of the several Parishes, and Approved and Sworn by the Justices at the <hi>Quarter-Sessions.</hi> And of their Qualities and Offices I shall speak anon.</p>
            <p>Having thus appointed, as I think, proper <hi>Overseers</hi> and <hi>Executers</hi> of my Methods, I proceed to the Methods themselves: And, first, I propose to have some Conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient and Certain Division made of the Kingdom, each Division to consist of about Two or Three thousand Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies or Housholds; and so the Division that is already of Counties, where the Counties are small, and not po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous, may serve where they are larger. And likewise in the Great City of <hi>London</hi> the Division may be accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly. In every such Division, I propose to have <hi>Two publick Houses</hi> erected, the one to be both an <hi>Hospital</hi> and a <hi>Workhouse,</hi> and the other to be both a <hi>Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house</hi> and a <hi>Prison.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>Hospital Workhouse,</hi> I would have it built as cheap as possibly may be, that so there may be the more Relief and Comfort afforded to the <hi>Poor;</hi> which is the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:206544:5"/>best End of all Charitable Works. I propose to have it built in this manner, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To have one very large Room built pretty high, with only an Earthen Floor, and a Hearth in the midst of it; and round about this great Room, I would have abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of little low Rooms, as it were Cabbins opening in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the great Room, where I would have all the Winter a constant Fire kept, Day and Night, that so it might warm into the little Cabbins when their Doors were open, and might be as a Common Fire to all the Poor that lodg'd in them; and might likewise serve to dress their Meat, (there being no need of Rost, and for boil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in little Crocks, or Pipkins, this Fire will serve very well) and likewise to warm and dry their Clothes, and all other necessary Uses. This Fire may be made of the Cheapest Fuel in the respective Countries; and, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, One good great Fire can be kept much cheaper than a great many little ones. And, because there may be an Inconvenience in keeping this place too hot and close, I propose, That over the little Cabbins there may be Lattice-Windows into this great Room, to be quite open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed when it is thought convenient. Without the little Cabbins that are round the great Room, I propose, to have some Ground, wherein every <hi>Poor Body</hi> may have a little Garden to his or her respective Cabbin, and a Door to open outwards to the Garden, as well as one to open inwards to the Common Room. — But, some of the Cab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins I would have made opener and airier than the others, that so in them Children may lodge; as shall be shewn.</p>
            <p>Now, if to any Division one of these great Rooms, with the Cabbins about it, may not be sufficient to contain the Poor, there may be two, or more, built in the same man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner near together: But it will always be necessary to have one of this sort of Rooms kept distinctly for the Sick.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:206544:5"/>
            <p>But tho' there should be never so many of these Rooms together, yet one Common <hi>Bakehouse, Brewhouse,</hi> and <hi>Washhouse</hi> will serve them all, with some diversity of Vessels; and appointing different Days for different Works, in which the Labour of those Poor that are able, is still to be used. For <hi>Brewing,</hi> that may be out of a Common Stock, and every one may have his fit proportion of Beer measur'd out. For <hi>Baking,</hi> every one may Bake what he has occasion for in the Common Oven. I would have a kind of a homely Barn built, where they may work in the dry, those Works that cannot conveniently be done either in their little Cabbins or the common Fire-room.</p>
            <p>Lastly, I would have these Houses to be built in the most barren places, except those of the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Westminster,</hi> who know best where to place them. In all Divisions that border on the Sea, I would have these Houses built as nigh the Sea as may be, that so the Poor may have Employment about the Fishery, and may be the cheaper fed by the Plenty of Fish.</p>
            <p>Having thus contriv'd a Place of <hi>Being</hi> or <hi>Habitation,</hi> we are next to consider, Who are to be put into it; and then, What they are to do here. And,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> I would have all Persons who receive Collection, or who cannot well live without Collection at least, at those times when they can do little or nothing at Home (which is to be judg'd of by the aforesaid <hi>Fathers of the Poor</hi>) to be sent to this place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I would have all Sick, Lame, Disabled, and Bed-rid Persons to be sent hither.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I would have all the supernumerary Children that are more than their Parents can Maintain by their Honest <hi>Labour</hi> and <hi>Industry,</hi> to be sent to this place.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:206544:6"/>
            <p>And then, Secondly, For what they are to do in this place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> I do suppose that there are no Persons so Old or Decrepit, but that they may be able to do some Work or other which may gain something; and tho' this Gain be never so small, yet if it be constant, it will help to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Maintenance, and will also be an Ease and Comfort to the Poor Body, by amusing and diverting him from Thinking on his Poverty, or other Misery; and by seeing that he is able to do Something towards the Publick Good. For those that are altogether Help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, some of the Poor that are able, may have it for their Work to tend them, and some to tend and take care of the Children, especially the smallest, who may be lodg'd in the widest or airiest Cabbins, One or more, with the Poor Women that are fittest to tend them. And sometimes the Mothers of a great many small Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren may be taken into the <hi>Hospital</hi> to tend their own and other's Children. But, I suppose that Children of Five or Six Years old may be capable of some Work that may give some little Assistance towards their Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. I do not presume, That the Work of the Poor should be able to maintain them, but so far as it helps towards it, so far the Publick Charge is eased; and, perhaps, it may go much farther than People do now apprehend, especially in that Frugal way of Living that I propose for All in this <hi>Hospital-Workhouse.</hi> For,</p>
            <p n="1">1st, For their <hi>Cloathing,</hi> I propose, That every one, in the Winter, have a Wastcoat, Coat and Breeches for the Men, and a Wastcoat, Petticoat, and Gown for the Women, the Gown being not open before, but coming down like an Upper Petticoat, and Lac'd before; and all this to be of coarse white Cloth, that so it may be wash'd when
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:206544:6"/>there is Occasion. In the Summer the Men need not have Wastcoats, nor the Women Under-Petticoats; the Men may have a coarse Linnen Neckcloth, and the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men a coarse Handkerchief about their Necks. For the Children, if small, they may be all cloath'd alike in one close Gown lac'd before, of the same White Cloth: But, if the Males are big, they may have Breeches of the same Cloth, and a Close-bodied Coat or Wastcoat: There may be added to every one some coarse Linnen to wear next them. Of these Habits each Person should have two Suits, that the one may be worn while the other is wash'd and clean'd; and two Suits together worn alternately, will last as long as two new Suits given the one after the other. This for their <hi>Clothes,</hi> then for their <hi>Diet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be remember'd I propos'd a <hi>Garden to every Cabbin,</hi> which may be planted with <hi>Cabbages, Carrots, Turnips, Potatoes,</hi> and the like, by those of the Poor that are able to do it; and a little Salt <hi>Beef</hi> or <hi>Bacon</hi> with the said Roots or Herbs, will go a good way. They may likewise have good boyling <hi>Pease</hi> provided for them, with <hi>Broth, Milk, Brown Bread,</hi> and the cheapest <hi>Cheese,</hi> and the like, at the Discretion of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> always contriving to have the <hi>Diet</hi> that is least expensive, provided it be wholsom.</p>
            <p>Having said as much as is necessary of the <hi>Hospital-Workhouse,</hi> I proceed now to the <hi>Prison-Workhouse,</hi> about which there needs little more <hi>Contrivance,</hi> than to have it built strong enough, and so as to keep every Person apart hard at Work.</p>
            <p>Several sorts of the <hi>Hardest Works,</hi> and most <hi>Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial,</hi> such as, if a <hi>Man</hi> or <hi>Woman</hi> be kept close to them, they may earn considerably more than their Expence, are to be found out for those that are detain'd in the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:206544:7"/>
               <hi>Prison Workhouse:</hi> And, that they may be able to go through with such Works, they should be fed with course, but hearty Fare.</p>
            <p>And for their <hi>Clothing,</hi> there is no need of any more, at least, for the great <hi>Malefactors</hi> but just to cover their Shame. These <hi>Prison-Workhouses</hi> I would have always to be in some City or great Town, that being severe Prisons, they may be well guarded; and that the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Sight of them may deter the more from those Vices that bring Persons into such Punishment. And also, that the <hi>Criminals</hi> being not suffer'd to wag abroad, may be the easier provided both of <hi>Food</hi> and <hi>Work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Into these <hi>Prison-Workhouses</hi> I would have sent,</p>
            <p n="1">I. 1st, All <hi>Robbers on the Highway, Housebreakers, Clippers</hi> and <hi>Coiners, Pickpockets,</hi> and the like, there to be kept till by the Overplus of what they gain by their Labour, they have made ample Satisfaction to all whom they have wrong'd; till they have paid for their Taking; and till they have acquir'd such a Habit of Industry and Faring hard, that they may be trusted again among <hi>Honest People.</hi> And, after all that, the Correctors ought to make them either work there till they have given something to these Houses, that have done them so much good, or to take an Obligation of them to do so when they have got Something in the World; the forfeiture of which Bond should be to return to those <hi>Prison-Workhouses.</hi> And in this Method it is observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that <hi>Clippers</hi> and <hi>Coiners,</hi> who have done the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> so much Injury, that they can never make it Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, will be kept here in <hi>Hard Slavery</hi> as long as they live: As, indeed, it is sit such <hi>Mischievous Beasts</hi> should be ever kept up in Close Durance.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:206544:7"/>
            <p>But because in <hi>Robbing</hi> and <hi>House-breaking</hi> there often happens <hi>Murder,</hi> and by the Law of God, <hi>He that sheds Man's Blood, by Man shall his Blood be shed;</hi> I would have this Horrible Wickedness punish'd with <hi>Death.</hi> But yet I do not know but it might terrifie some Men, more especially such as are of Atheistical Opinions, or such as through a Habit of <hi>Idleness</hi> and <hi>Luxury</hi> dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Work</hi> and <hi>Hard Fare</hi> more than <hi>Death;</hi> to put them first in this <hi>Prison-Workhouse,</hi> and there using them much harder in all respects than any other <hi>Criminals,</hi> every day Scourging them till the Blood comes, and reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them with their Villainous Murder; and in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to keep them till by their Labour they have made some sort of <hi>Restitution</hi> for the Damage that happen'd to any one by that Murder, or to the Publick, by the Loss of two Members of the Commonwealth; that is, of the Person murder'd, and of the Murderer, who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by forfeited his Life. And when he hath paid these Debts, let him also pay the Debt that he oweth the Law of his Blood.</p>
            <p n="2">II. 2dly, I would have sent into this <hi>Prison Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house</hi> all Prostitutes, of one or the other Sex, and all that live upon <hi>Bawdery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. 3dly, All <hi>Fraudulent Debtors,</hi> who are as bad, if not worse than <hi>Robbers.</hi> It should be in the Power of <hi>Creditors,</hi> who can prove their Debts, to cast their Debtors that will not pay into this Prison; and there, when the Correctors have examin'd the Case, if they find a Man to be in Debt meerly through <hi>Misfortune,</hi> they shall move the Creditor and others to be Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to him, and do what they can to Compound his Debts, and to put him again into a way of Living: And if they cannot do this, they shall order him to be used kindly, allowing some small matter to his Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:206544:8"/>out of his Labour. But if, upon Enquiry, they shall find the Debtor contracted those Debts with a purpose to cheat his Creditor, then such a Debtor is to be used in all respects as a <hi>Thief,</hi> he being such a <hi>Thief</hi> as a Man cannot be aware of.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. 4thly, To this place should be sent all <hi>Wandering Beggars,</hi> all <hi>Petty Chapmen, Pedlers, Tinkers,</hi> and the like, who may be, and often are, of a very lewd and wicked Life, being under no Bodies Inspection, nor being to be found to be punish'd for their Cheats and Thefts, by reason of their Wandering Life, and bearing likewise no publick Burdens or Taxes; and so are no way bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial, but very injurious to the Commonweal.</p>
            <p>In like manner, after the <hi>Hospital-Workhouses</hi> are setled, if any pretend to Travel with Passes, among whom there are now many Cheats, they may be clap'd up into these <hi>Prison-Workhouses,</hi> because that there may be Care taken, that those that have truly need to pass from one place to another, subsisting upon Charity, may be reliev'd, and sent from one <hi>Hospital-Workhouse</hi> to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, doing Something for their Living, during their stay in each <hi>Hospital-Workhouse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">V. 5thly, All <hi>Notoriously-Idle</hi> and <hi>Riotous Persons,</hi> who Spend much beyond their Earning or Income, should be sent to these <hi>Prison-Workhouses,</hi> there to be kept to Hard Labour and Hard Diet, till it may be reasonably hoped they are Cured of that <hi>Idleness</hi> and <hi>Extravagance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All these Persons are to be us'd better or worse, with Regard to their <hi>Lodging, Clothing, Food, Correction</hi> or <hi>Time of durance;</hi> according to their different Crimes, and what may tend best to their effectual Cure: And so much must rest upon the Justice and Discretion of the <hi>Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors,</hi> who, as you will see by what follows, are to give an Account of what they do.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:206544:8"/>
            <p>Having thus spoke of this <hi>Prison-Workhouse,</hi> and who are to be put into it, and how they are to be <hi>Fed, Cloth'd</hi> and <hi>Handl'd,</hi> there is one thing yet remains, which may be thought strange; that is, I would have all these wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Men and wicked Women, that are in these places, married together, if there be enough of each Sex, and they are not married before. But here I except the <hi>Murderers,</hi> of whom I would have no Offspring: For the rest, let them be brought to Marry one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; which will be no hard matter. And, that their Matching may be little or no hinderance to the Work either of the Men or of the Women; and also, that they may produce strong and healthy Children, I propose, That they may accompany together but once in a week, every <hi>Saturday,</hi> about Three of the Clock; the Man and his Wife may cease their Labour, and be brought toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and so Sup and Lodge together, and the next day be parted again; where both Men and Women, in seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Divisions of a Room where they cannot see each other, may be brought to hear Divine Service and a Sermon; then being had to their respective little work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Rooms again, they may lodge by themselves, and the next Morning early return to their Work.</p>
            <p>As for the Women that prove with Child, they may nevertheless be held to their Work, tho' in some de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree abated; and when they are brought to Bed, the Children shall be remov'd to the <hi>Hospital Workhouse,</hi> there to be suckl'd by some poor Women, or brought up by Hand; and the Mothers, as soon as they are able, shall be forced to return to their hard Labour. But when the Man and the Woman have wrought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves out of the <hi>Prison-Workhouse,</hi> they shall have their Children sent them, if they are able to keep them.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:206544:9"/>
            <p>I am sensible it will be objected, That in the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of both the <hi>Hospital</hi> and <hi>Prison-Workhouse</hi> I bring a needless and mighty Burthen upon the Publick, in loading it with the Charge of so many Children. But I think it a Fault in any Constitution, not to encourage the encrease of Lawful Children, especially when they are like to be train'd up in all Frugality and Industry, as these will be. And it may be so contriv'd, that in a little time this may be no Burthen at all to the Publick; for, the <hi>Fathers of the Poor</hi> may have Power given them so oblige every one that hath been brought up in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy in the <hi>Hospital-Workhouse,</hi> after they can get more than is necessary for their own Maintenance, to pay to the <hi>Hospital-Workhouse,</hi> the Men as much as will train up two Infants, and the Women as much as will train up one, in like manner as they had been trained up themselves; and that under pain of being sent to the <hi>Prison-Workhouse.</hi> And then, considering how frugally Children will be kept in the <hi>Hospital-Workhouses,</hi> how soon they will be able to get their own Living, or Something towards it, and how many Charitable Gifts will be sent to those places, where People will be satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied 'twill be so well employ'd. This training up of a numerous company of Children will be found to be lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no Charge, and yet a mighty Advantage to the Publick. It will also prevent a great deal of <hi>Sin,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage <hi>Marriage,</hi> and encrease a <hi>healthy</hi> and <hi>well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurtur'd People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come now to speak of the Privileges, Powers, and Duties of the <hi>Fathers of the Poor,</hi> and <hi>Correctors of the Wicked,</hi> who are to be the Overseers and Executers of these Methods, and upon whose Discretion, Care, and Fidelity all the Success of the Design will depend.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:206544:9"/>
            <p>And, 1st, of their <hi>Privileges.</hi> It is but reasonable that such Persons who are so beneficial to the Publick, should have some Privileges, and therefore I think it fit that they be excus'd from the Burthen of any other Office, from Serving on <hi>Juries,</hi> and the like; and that, as Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates of a lower degree, they have Precedence, and their Wives likewise, of all of their Rank and Condition, that at their Election they have presented them at the Publick Charge a Walking-staff with a Silver Head, with the Pictures of <hi>Justice</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> engrav'd upon it, for a Badge of their Office and Authority.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, For their <hi>Powers.</hi> They should, I think, have the Power of perpetual Constables, tho' not obliged to act any of the Constable's Office, but when their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties hereafter mention'd oblige them. They should al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so have Power and Authority to enquire and demand of any Person who appears to live Idley and Riotously, and to spend more than he or she can have honestly coming in, how it is that they maintain such Expence: And if they do deny or refuse to give an Account, that then the <hi>Corrector of the Wicked</hi> have Power in himself to send such a Person immediately away to the <hi>Prison-Workhouse,</hi> and that all Persons be aiding and assisting to him in so doing. But if the said Suspected Person shall offer some Account of the Answering of his Income to his Expence, and that Account be not satisfactory, to prevent the Effects of Private <hi>Malice,</hi> the <hi>Corrector</hi> shall have the Person before a <hi>Justice of Peace,</hi> who with the Assistance of another Justice, may examin him; and, if they see cause, may by their Joint-Warrant send him to the <hi>Prison-Workhouse.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:206544:10"/>
            <p>In like manner each <hi>Father of the Poor</hi> shall have Power to Examin, how any Poor man supports his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Children; and if he find that such Poor man hath more than he can support by his honest Labour, he shall take from him so many as he thinks sit, and send them, whether the Man and his Wife will or no, to the <hi>Hospital-Workhouse;</hi> and when he seeth convenient, send the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther also with the Children, where the Father may see them every <hi>Sunday,</hi> provided he bring enough to feed them and him for that day.</p>
            <p>And in case, by reason of this Dependance, any La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring man should turn Idle or Sottish, he may be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to work, by the same Remedy that is provided for all other idle Persons; that is, by being sent to the <hi>Prison Workhouse,</hi> if nothing else will reform him; for it is not design'd, that any man should be eas'd of any more Burthen than what he cannot by his honest Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry support.</p>
            <p>As to the Apprehension of these <hi>House-breakers, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupters of the King's Coyn, Pickpockets,</hi> all such as live on <hi>Bawdery, Gypsies, Walking Beggars, Wandring Petty-chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and the like, this may still be left to the Usual Constables, and by a Justice's Warrant they may be sent to the <hi>Prison-Workhouse,</hi> where they will best be Corrected; that is, both punish'd and made bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>But, because this Duty is too often neglected by the Ordinary Officers, the Correctors may be impower'd first to complain to the Justices, and, if that will not do, by their own Authority to seize the abovesaid Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals, and send them to the <hi>Prison-Workhouse,</hi> where such Criminals shall remain, only paying double for their <hi>Diet,</hi> till at a General Court the Truth of their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:206544:10"/>Case be known, and then suitable Disciplin shall be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed them.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly, For the <hi>Duties</hi> of these <hi>Fathers of the Poor,</hi> and <hi>Correctors of the Wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These will be very <hi>many</hi> and <hi>great;</hi> and therefore none should be chosen into this Office but Ancient, Grave, Substantial, Prudent, and Pious Men; and when they are elected, they should take a Solemn Oath, That they will Faithfully Discharge, to the best of their Skill, the Great Office they have undertaken, and make it their Study and Endeavour to promote True Justice and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>I propose, That the Whole Body of these <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Correctors</hi> meet the First Day of every Month, unless the First Day happen to be <hi>Sunday,</hi> and then they may meet the next Day, which meeting shall be call'd their <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Court:</hi> Let them meet in a full Body one Month at the <hi>Hospital-Workhouse,</hi> and the next Month at the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son-Workhouse.</hi> When they meet at the <hi>Hospital-Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house,</hi> they shall chuse out a Committee of Ten, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them necessary Instructions, send them to the <hi>Prison-workhouse,</hi> who shall be term'd <hi>The General Court at the Prison-workhouse</hi> for that Month: And so, in like manner, when they meet all at the <hi>Prison-workhouse,</hi> shall they do by the <hi>Hospital-workhouse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, at the meeting of these General Courts, either of the Whole Body, or of the Committee of Ten, which shall be always taken as a General Court, there shall be a short Sermon or Exhortation on the Subject of <hi>Justice</hi> or <hi>Charity,</hi> made by some Minister of the Division: And let it be observ'd, That every Parson or Vicar in each Division shall have Power to come, if he pleases, into every General Court of that Division, and may Advise,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:206544:11"/>Act, and Vote in the said Court, as any other <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Corrector</hi> may; but shall be obliged to no other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, besides making his Exhortation in his turn.</p>
            <p>As soon as the Court is sate, they shall chuse a <hi>Chair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> and a <hi>Clerk</hi> out of their own body, for that time, that so all may understand the Methods of proceeding, and to avoid multiplying Officers, who are always a Charge, and often an occasion of Corruption and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice.</p>
            <p>The first thing the Court shall proceed in at the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son workhouse</hi> shall be, to call before them all the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons that have been sent thither since the last Session; and they shall hear their respective Cases, and award them Just Discipline: But, if the Case seem difficult, and there be only the Committee of Ten sitting, they may deser the Condemning to Discipline till the next Court, when the Whole Body will meet there, keeping the suspected Criminal only upon the Charge of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing double what his Diet cost, for the benefit of the House, which is no more than Men pay in Inns; And he may be obliged to pay either out of what he hath, or out of his Labour.</p>
            <p>The next thing to be consider'd by the Court is, To contrive the most proper and beneficial Works to be done at that time by the Criminals: And, for this reason, the Correctors of the Wicked should be chosen, at least a great part of them, out of several Trades, that they may the better know how to find out and prescribe such Works.</p>
            <p>I think it no Objection to say, That perhaps the Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals will not do the Works as they should be done; since <hi>Scourging,</hi> and <hi>Pinching with Hunger</hi> will tame the highest Spirit, and make them do even what you please. And if some should dye under the Discipline, this, in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:206544:11"/>respect of the high Criminals, who are to be us'd the most severely, is no more than when they had deserv'd by our present Law. But yet, by the Prudence of the Correctors, this may always be avoided.</p>
            <p>Before the breaking up of the Court at the <hi>Prison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workhouse,</hi> if the whole Court Sir, there shall be chosen out of the Body Ten Persons to be <hi>Stewards</hi> for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing Month. If only the Committee of Ten Sit, they shall be the Stewards themselves.</p>
            <p>The Duty of these Stewards shall be as followeth.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Two of them shall buy in Provisions for the House.</item>
               <item>Two shall see the Work brought in and carried out.</item>
               <item>Two shall see Due Correction executed.</item>
               <item>Two shall Pay the Inferiour Officers, that inflict the Discipline, or carry the Provisions or Work to and fro, and to take an Account of what is laid Out and Earn'd.</item>
               <item>The other Two to draw up the whole Account brought them by their Eight Brethren, and to consider it, and make their best Remarks upon it; and present it, with their Remarks, to the next full Court. And, at least, two of these Stewards should lodge in the <hi>Prison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workhouse,</hi> in some convenient Room set aside for that purpose.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The like Course is to be taken for the <hi>Hospital-work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house,</hi> Ten <hi>Stewards</hi> are to be chosen monthly.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Two to see Provisions collected and brought in.</item>
               <item>Two to provide proper Work.</item>
               <item>Two to see any Irregularity corrected.</item>
               <item>Two to pay Necessary Officers, and make a state of the Receipts and Disbursements.</item>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:206544:12"/>
               <item>And Two to take an Account of all that hath been done by their Brethren; to make their Remarks, and to give them in to the next full meeting.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And this Burthen will not be great upon any man, because in a Hundred and twenty <hi>Father-Correctors,</hi> which is the least number I propose for every Division, it can come to a Man's Turn but twice in a Year.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Hospital-workhouses</hi> that are in Inland Counties, the Fathers of the Poor need only breed up the Children to be fit for Servants to Husbandmen, or to be Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices to Handicraft-Trades; and to be taught to Read is Learning enough for them: But in <hi>Hospital-workhouses</hi> that are near the Sea, those Boys that are capable, shall be instructed in all the Art of Navigation; and All shall be taught the Skill of Catching and Ordering Fish; Boats and Fishing-Tackle, and able Persons to assist, being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided at the charge of the House.</p>
            <p>To every <hi>Hospital-workhouse</hi> there shall always belong an easie Waggon, with two or three Horses, to fetch the Sick and Decrepit Poor to the House, or to carry such from <hi>Hospital-workhouse</hi> to <hi>Hospital-workhouse,</hi> in their passage home; which will free the Country of a great deal of Charge and Trouble.</p>
            <p>In every <hi>Hospital-workhouse</hi> I would have some private place appointed, to be visited at certain times by the Women of the House, to which any young Children may be brought, and none shall take notice or enquire who brought them, or from whom they were sent; but all such Children shall be taken in, and brought up by the House. This may prevent many Execrable Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and be a Benefit to many poor Infants, who, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through their Parents Shame to make their Case known, or Despair of Relief, might suffer very much
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:206544:12"/>or be lost. It can't be objected, That this will encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the begetting Unlawful Children; since care is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before, that Lewd Persons be sent to the <hi>Prison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workhouse,</hi> and there married to those of their own strain; which will prevent such Wickedness much more than any Means now us'n. As to the Charge this will bring upon the Publick, that hath been answer'd alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: And indeed, it is demonstrable, that the Encrease the Publick Stock may have from the Labour of One from ten to twenty five years old, will more than dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or treble pay for the Charge such a one stood the Publick in, in the time of Infancy: And it is all the Reason in the World that such a one should be oblig'd to pay this Debt to the Publick.</p>
            <p>For the Instruction of poor Children in Religion, the <hi>Fathers of the Poor</hi> shall take care that all be taught the <hi>Church-Catechism;</hi> and that the Children, as soon as they can learn it, shall constantly say the <hi>Lord's Prayer</hi> and <hi>Creed,</hi> rising and going to Bed; at Noon the <hi>Psalms</hi> for the Day, and the <hi>Chapters,</hi> shall be read by the Children, and the <hi>Letany,</hi> with the <hi>General Thanks,</hi> giving the Prayer of St. <hi>Chrysostom,</hi> and the <hi>Blessing,</hi> shall be read by one of the gravest men in the House, all making the Responses. At night, some such grave Person (which if there be none other fit, may be one of the Fathers that is then Steward in the House) shall call the Youth, and appoint some of them to read the <hi>Psalms</hi> for the Day, and the <hi>Chapter,</hi> and then he shall reverently rehearse the <hi>Lord's Prayer,</hi> and the <hi>Collect</hi> that follows it in the <hi>Communion Service,</hi> and so proceed to the <hi>Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> after every one of which <hi>All</hi> present shall make that Prayer, to beg Forgiveness of God for any Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression against that Commandment, and His Grace to enable them to Keep it better for the time to come, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:206544:13"/>aloud, <hi>Lord, have Mercy,</hi> &amp;c. I advise the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments at Night, that so, by them, every one may examin his Actions of the Day past. After the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, I would have the two Prayers in the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination</hi> us'd, the first of which begins. <hi>O most mighty God, and merciful Father,</hi> — and the second, <hi>Turn thou us, Good Lord,</hi> &amp;c. only leaving out the word <hi>Fasting.</hi> Then shall follow the Prayer for Absolution in the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination;</hi> then the Prayer for the whole Church-mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, and one or two of the Collects in the Communion Service; with <hi>The Peace of God,</hi> &amp;c. On <hi>Sundays</hi> all that can shall repair to the Parish-Church; and for the Sick and Decrepit, the Minister of the Parish may be desir'd at convenient times to visit them.</p>
            <p>At the Court held at the <hi>Hospital-Workhouse,</hi> there shall be a strict Enquiry made into the state of the House, what hath been earn'd in it, what hath been gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to it, what hath and must be expended, and what is wanting in the Income to answer the Expence. And in my Opinion, they ought always to have a Months Provision ready beforehand.</p>
            <p>Now, if neither the <hi>Gifts</hi> nor <hi>Earnings</hi> will answer the necessary Expence, what is wanting is to be levy'd on the whole Division, of Two or Three thousand Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, by the Court, in as equal a manner as may be.</p>
            <p>It is my Opinion, That the Poor should not be kept to exceeding hard Labour, but that within an honest Industry they may live Comfortably; the Charity of their Brethren supplying what That cannot obtain.</p>
            <p>Exceeding Hard Labour is to be the Punishment of the Other House; but <hi>Poverty,</hi> which is no Fault, ought not to be punish'd. In the Levies that are made on the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision, it may be order'd, That Men send in their <hi>Quota's</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:206544:13"/>either in Money or Provisions, at a reasonable value; but the <hi>Fathers of the Poor</hi> are not to be charged there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, because their Care and Attendance on this Charity is sufficient for their Part, they being neither to have any Stipend, or to make any sort of Gain by their Office; only the Charge they are at in conveying the Poor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the Workhouses, is to be allow'd them. And while they stay at the <hi>Hospital-workhouse,</hi> they shall only lodge in some of the best Cabbins, and have the same Diet that the most-favour'd of the Poor have.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Prison-workhouse,</hi> I do suppose it will more than maintain it self; it must be very negligently look'd after if it doth not; for this is to be a place of Pain and Misery, there being few, or none, to be long kept here, but what deserve not to live; and surely, if they be kept to the Hardest Labour, working almost naked, they must Earn much more than they Eat.</p>
            <p>And indeed, by reason of this state of the <hi>Prison-work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house,</hi> I do presume, there will ever be a good Stock of Money beforehand, out of which I would have lent to Poor Industrious People small Sums to follow their little Trades with, but obliging themselves either to pay the same in a little time, or to render themselves in the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son-workhouse,</hi> to satisfie their Debt by their Labour.</p>
            <p>Out of this Stock also I would have paid to every one that discovers and causes to be apprehended any <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayman, House-breaker, Diminisher of the King's Coin,</hi> or <hi>Pickpocket,</hi> 10 <hi>l.</hi> for one that lives in <hi>Bawdery</hi> 5 <hi>l.</hi> for every Wanderer, whether <hi>Beggar, Gypsie,</hi> or <hi>Pedler, &amp;c.</hi> 50 <hi>s.</hi> Which Money shall be Reimbursed to the House, out of the Work of the said Criminal.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:206544:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Lastly,</hi> For the keeping all in due order, I propose, That the <hi>Fathers-Correctors,</hi> at every Quarter-Sessions of the Justices of the Peace, present a true state of the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses to the Justices, who may inspect their Books, and overlook all their Proceedings, and amend what they find amiss. And from them also there may be an Appeal to the Judge of the Assize; and, if need be, to the King and Council.</p>
            <p>Having now finish'd my designed Proposal, I shall first represent some Conveniencies of it, which are not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd in the Body of the Design; and, secondly, Answer some Objections that may be made against it, and so leave it to take its Fate.</p>
            <p>And, <hi>First,</hi> This will be a certain Means of making all Manufactures very cheap among us, when all Hands that are capable of doing any thing are continually employ'd: And how great an Advantage it must be to our Foreign Trade, to have our Manufactures cheap, no body can be ignorant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Out of the <hi>Hospital-workhouses,</hi> that is, of the Poor Children that are grown up, and likewise out of the <hi>Prison-workhouses,</hi> of those that are brought to a Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of Industry and Frugality, our Plantations may be plentifully and well furnish'd; which will likewise tend to the Advantage of the Foreign Trade, and much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease the Riches of the Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Out of both sorts of Workhouses the King may be furnish'd with able Souldiers; and out of the Houses near the Sea, with good Seamen: But then I think it reasonable, that when Persons are taken out either for the Plantations, or for Sea and Land-Service, some Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensation be made to the Houses; to the <hi>Prison Workhouse,</hi> to supply what the Person taken forth had been condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to earn; and to the <hi>Hospital-Workhouse,</hi> for the train<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:206544:14"/>up more Infants: But, I think, it ought to be obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that none be taken out of the <hi>Prison-Workhouse</hi> till they may reasonably be suppos'd to be brought to a Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of <hi>Frugality</hi> and <hi>Industry,</hi> lest they do them that take them forth more Harm than Good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Out of the <hi>Hospital-workhouse</hi> any Person that wants a good Servant, either for <hi>Husbandry,</hi> for the <hi>Harvest,</hi> or any other sort of Work, may be supplied with one for his purpose, because that he may there have certain information of such Servants Conditions and Qualifications.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> In the <hi>Prison workhouses</hi> no Unhappy Prisoner will Suffer more than he hath deserv'd; as poor <hi>Debtors</hi> now often do in Jayls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Any Person that wants Work at any time, may find it in the <hi>Hospital-workhouses,</hi> where the <hi>Fathers of the Poor</hi> are to take care that the Poor never want Work, tho' they Earn never so little; which will always be some help towards their Maintenance, and Ease the charge of Collections.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> In the <hi>Hospital-workhouse</hi> the Children of Souldiers and Seamen in the Service of their King and Country, may be provided for; which will be a great Encouragement to their Fathers to behave themselves Valiantly.</p>
            <p>And now to the <hi>Objections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>First</hi> and Main <hi>Objection</hi> will be, <hi>Where will you have Money to build these</hi> Workhouses? To which I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, First, As to the <hi>Prison-workhouses,</hi> they will cost no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, because the Prisons and Houses of Correction may be turn'd into them: And whereas the Jayls now cost the Country Money, these <hi>Prison-workhouses,</hi> if well look'd after, will <hi>more than maintain</hi> themselves, and cause such as have injur'd the Publick, to make some Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:206544:15"/>to it by their Labour; whereas now Rogues live very Idely and Wickedly in Jayls, and when they are hang'd, can do no more good. And it is pity that a Man should be rear'd up to do the Publick no Service, but only Mischief.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Hospital-Workhouses,</hi> in the <hi>Plain way</hi> I have propos'd to build them (for certainly Poor People have no need of Palaces) One Years Collection paid before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, would certainly do it, and the Collections for the Poor will ever after be abated: Besides, it may very reasonably be expected, that there will be <hi>many Bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Contributions</hi> to so Good and Certain a Piece of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and, perhaps, many of the Charitable Donations that are up and down in the Kingdom, may be better employ'd in this way, for the advantage of the Poor, which was the Design of the Donors, than in the Ways they now are.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It may be Objected, That <hi>This, as all other Good Designs, may in time grow cold, and be neglected.</hi> But against this Danger, I think, the chusing such Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers as are neither too High to look after it, nor too Low to have any Interest, or however, is a Sufficient Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion; for, by this very means, that is, by chusing a great many <hi>able Citizens</hi> for Governours, the Hospitals in <hi>London</hi> are taken better care of than any other <hi>Charitable Works</hi> I know in the Kingdom: And, from them, in part, it was that I took my Model.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It may be Objected, That <hi>This takes the Judging of Criminals out of the hands of the Judges of Assize.</hi> That it doth not wholly, because that to them there is always an <hi>Appeal;</hi> and besides, the Sentencing of any great Offender to the aforesaid Punishments, may, if it be thought best, still be reserv'd to them; and so this Method that is propos'd will only alter the Punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:206544:15"/>for the better. As to the Damage <hi>Keepers</hi> and other Officers may receive hereby, that may be Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died, by putting them, if they are honest, into like Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in these Reformed Prisons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lastly,</hi> It may be said, That <hi>it will be difficult to find enow Persons sufficiently hard-hearted, to execute Necessary Disciplines upon all Criminals.</hi> To which I answer, That great part of this Work may be done by one Criminal upon another, especially where any Criminal complains, That One in the same Prison seduced him; he may be put to Execute the Discipline upon that his Seducer. And then <hi>Debtors</hi> that are used favourably, and those that have been amended by the <hi>Prison-Workhouse,</hi> and are ready to be manumitted, will not be unwilling to use the same means on others, for <hi>Their Amendment;</hi> which is not <hi>Hardheartedness,</hi> but <hi>True Charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>